All right. Good morning, church. How are you guys doing? Hope you're doing well. Yeah, so if we
haven't met before, my name is Josh. I've been part of this church for 15 years now, and I'm in the
married group as well. Why don't we turn our Bibles to 2 Thessalonians chapter 3. We're going
to be finishing up this book today. And as you're turning there, so my wife and I got married a few
years ago, and one of the things I've discovered about being married that I think is like underrated
is specialization. Anyone affirm that? Any married people affirm that? Specialization, right? So as
a married couple, you start to kind of slowly figure out, okay, these chores and responsibilities,
yeah, I like doing these, I'll do these, these things, oh, I really, I don't like doing that,
but hey, this other person, they're really good at that, or they like doing it, or, you know,
and eventually, you kind of settle into your area of expertise, and one day, you're just like,
wow, I haven't had to think about that in a really long time, and it's really nice.
So, for an example, one time, I was talking to my wife, Tiff, I thought I was being nice here,
and I said, you know, I think we've been doing a really good job
keeping our bathroom clean.
Like, we've been doing great.
And she says, yeah, it's because I vacuum every week
and I wipe down all the surfaces every week
and, like, every few weeks I, like, deep clean the shower.
So, yeah, that's probably why you feel like that.
And I was like, oh, okay.
Oh, thank you so much.
I really appreciate you.
I love you so much.
You're the best.
There's a lot of things like that, right?
Another thing she does is,
apparently I had no idea how she did this,
but every few days she will go into our guest bathroom
and she will rotate the towels.
So turn it around and the next day she'll swap them
and then the next day she'll fold them inside out
so that we aren't wiping our hands
on the same part of the towel every time.
And I was like, well, I would never think to do that,
but thanks, I appreciate that.
Um, and you know, vice versa, there's some stuff that I take care of, you know, as well. I'm more
in charge of like mowing the lawn, doing most of the laundry, house maintenance, uh, picking up dead
animals, that kind of stuff. Um, so specialization is great. And, um, as a side benefit, you also get
to roast each other because you can say, oh, my spouse, you know, my spouse doesn't even know you
have to like register your vehicle every year and pay for that and do the sticker. Or my spouse,
I don't think my spouse knows how to open the fridge door because they just don't know what food
we have at any time. You can guess who's who in that relationship. But this all works, right? I
think this all still works in the relationship if each person is contributing what they're specialized
to the relationship, but it can also sometimes feel like, man, I'm spending a lot of effort,
a lot of mind space thinking about this thing that this other person might not even know that I'm
taking care of. And sometimes it can feel bad. Sometimes it can feel bad, and if that's not
communicated or addressed, that's what can lead to sometimes feeling like, oh, I feel like I'm
being taken for granted. Or, you know, I feel underappreciated. And in the long term, if that
keeps going on, that can hurt the relationship. So in our passage today, Paul is going to address
a group of people in the church that have been taking other people's hard work for granted.
And it is starting to cause real problems in the church. And he's going to have some strong
instructions, even consequences for what to do in that situation. So let's get into our passage for
today. I'm going to read verses 1 to 5 first, and in this part, we'll just see Paul kind of wrapping
up and summarizing what he's talking about before and reminding the Thessalonians of their mission
to be faithful and loving witnesses even as they endure persecution. So the church's mission,
and be faithful and loving through persecution.
Let's read verses one to five.
Finally, brothers and sisters, pray for us
that the word of the Lord may speed ahead
and be honored as happened among you,
that we may be delivered from evil and wicked men.
For not all have faith, but the Lord is faithful.
He will establish you and guard you against the evil one.
And we have confidence in the Lord about you,
that you are doing and will do the things that we command.
May the Lord direct your hearts to the love of God
and to the steadfastness of Christ.
So for those of us who were here the past few weeks,
you might remember that Paul and the Thessalonians
are going through kind of similar situations.
The Thessalonian church is going through persecution.
If you were here two weeks ago,
Pastor Sam talked about enduring persecution
while hoping in Jesus' return.
I'll remind you of this passage, 2 Thessalonians 1, verses 3 to 4.
It says, Paul says,
And Paul's asking for prayer for himself as well, right?
Because he's also facing opposition.
He's facing opposition from people that he calls wicked and evil people who are blocking the spread of the word of the Lord.
And this might be people who are, I don't know, spreading false teaching, causing fear or confusion in the church.
That's what we talked about last week, right?
If you were here, we talked about people who were saying, oh, the day of the Lord has already arrived.
And that was causing a lot of fear and confusion in the church.
or it could just be normal persecution from Roman authorities or Jewish leaders.
But they're both going through this opposition.
But in verse 3, Paul encourages the Thessalonians.
He says, but God is faithful.
He's going to protect the Thessalonians and Paul from the evil one.
They're going to be guarded even as they go through persecution.
So here's what the Thessalonians are called to do.
They're called to stay faithful.
They're called to stay steadfast through persecution, continue to grow in love,
and continue to follow the teachings of Paul and the apostles.
And in verse 4, he kind of slips this in.
He says, we have confidence in the Lord about you that you are doing
and will do the things that we command.
So Paul is kind of preparing them to hear some difficult things that he's going to say.
And it will be difficult, but he wants them to take it seriously, obey them.
So what is Paul's command here?
Let's keep reading, and we'll see that Paul is going to address this problem of idleness,
living in idleness, which is disrupting the church's mission.
So let's read verses 6 to 12.
Now we command you, brothers and sisters, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ,
that you keep away from any brother who is walking in idleness
and not in accord with the tradition that you receive from us.
for you yourselves know that you ought to imitate us
because we were not idle when we were with you
nor did we eat anyone's bread without paying for it
but with toil and labor we worked night and day
that we might give you in ourselves
oh sorry that we may not be a burden to any of you
it was not because we don't have that right
but it was to give you in ourselves an example to imitate
for even when we were with you
we would hear that some among you, we would give you this command, I'm sorry, we would give you
this command, if anyone is not willing to work, let him not eat. For we hear that some among you
walk in idleness, not busy at work, but busy bodies. Now such persons we command and encourage
in the Lord Jesus Christ to do their work quietly and earn their own living. So my wife is on
sabbatical this summer. She works at this place where, you know, you get this amazing perk. You get
to take a few months off every few years. And, you know, when I was assigned this passage, I made
the obvious joke, like, Tiff, what are you going to do? Paul says you can't eat this summer, right?
Maybe you have to go on a liquid fast or something. I don't know. But no, this passage isn't about
people who are taking a break from work. It's not about people who are retired or can't work
for whatever reason, right? These are people Paul is calling idle. So who are these idlers?
Who are these idlers that don't do anything, they just stay home and lie around? So we can notice
that Paul's not just talking about people who don't work, right? He is talking about people who
are choosing not to work. Verse 10, Paul says, anyone not willing to work should not eat, right?
So there's a choice involved here.
For whatever reason, they're choosing not to work.
And Paul thinks that they can work.
So look at verse 12.
Paul is commanding them to work quietly and earn their own living.
So Paul assumes that they can work,
and this is a choice for whatever reason they're choosing not to work.
So why were some people choosing to be idle?
The reason's not totally clear.
It could be because of what we talked about last week.
There's some people who thought,
oh, the day of the Lord is already here,
or the day of the Lord's coming really, really soon,
so work is like, it's all going away anyway, right?
It's irrelevant, I don't have to work anymore.
That could be the reason here.
We don't know for sure.
One thing we do know for sure is that
this is not the first time that Paul
has had to address this issue, right?
This was a recurring issue,
and that might be why Paul speaks so strongly
about this issue here.
So we see in verse 10 again that Paul already addressed this when he was in person with the
Thessalonians, right? This was a problem already. He had to give them like a rule because some people
were living this way. Paul addresses this again in 1 Thessalonians chapter 4 verses 10 to 12.
Let me read that for you. But we urge you, brothers and sisters, to do this more and more
and to aspire to live quietly, to mind your own affairs,
to work with your hands as we instructed you,
so that you may walk properly before outsiders
and become dependent on no one.
So he addressed it a second time in 1 Thessalonians,
and now he's addressing it a third time in our passage today.
So that might explain why it's kind of ratcheted up a little bit,
because apparently his instructions the first few times didn't work.
now you might wonder how could anyone even afford to be idle right idleness in this economy
um but uh we see in verse 8 that the idlers were somehow living off of the financial resources
of others so paul is saying hey when we were with you we set an example of the opposite of idleness
right me and timothy and silas we worked really hard we were guests right we could have
received normal hospitality as guests, but we chose not to. We chose to work because we didn't
want to put a burden on others, and because we knew some of you needed an example to follow.
But apparently, instead of following this example, these idlers have become dependent
on the financial resources of others. But I want us to see something here, right?
The only reason the idlers could have survived
is because the church was already a place of generosity.
The church was already a place
where people were sacrificially loving,
contributing to help the needy, right?
That's the only reason why the idlers could survive.
So once again, I think we can see
that the Thessalonian church
was already living out its mission, right?
They're already being faithful, loving each other,
and in this specific way,
loving each other through generosity.
And I just want to point out,
this isn't unique to the Thessalonian church.
I think we know this.
In a lot of early church communities,
this was common.
A lot of us know Acts 2,
where the believers in Jerusalem
held everything in common, right?
They were selling their possessions
to take care of those in need.
In Acts 6, it mentions that same church
having some kind of daily distribution of food
for widows.
and in first timothy in the church of ephesus paul gives some instructions on taking care of
widows as well so this is a this is a pattern of generosity in the early church and of course this
comes from jesus right jesus taught his followers to see each other as brothers and sisters he taught
his followers that it's more blessed to give than to receive and of course he showed this by his
own love of people and his own giving himself in his death on the cross. So again, it's only
because the Thessalonians were already living out their mission, they're already practicing
love and generosity, that they began to have this kind of second order problem of people living in
idleness in the first place, right? So given all this, I think we can say that when Paul's talking
about idleness here, his meaning isn't that, okay, in the church, everyone is just responsible for
themselves. That's not what he's saying. He's not saying that if someone is in desperate need
and has nothing to eat, that, okay, it's their own fault, right? We don't have to care about that
because there were probably people like widows or sick people that couldn't work, right? And they
had to depend on the generosity of the church. And Paul isn't calling those people out as burdens,
right? That's not who Paul's talking about here. He's talking about the people who are choosing not
to work, who are choosing to live in idleness and taking advantage of the church's generosity. Those
are the people Paul is saying, you're putting a burden on the church. And this was causing some
serious relational disruption in the church. And to the point that Paul says there might be,
you know, there might have to be some consequences if this keeps going on. So let's reflect on
ourselves for a sec. I don't know if any of us are living in idleness. Anyone living in idleness
here? Most of us work a job, right? Most of us are busy. We work a job or we take care of our kids
or, you know, we take care of the church so it doesn't leak during the storm
or we, you know, we're students, we're hard at work at school.
But what about taking the hard work of others for granted, right?
What about taking others for granted?
I think that's a little bit more common for us.
Those of us who are married or maybe in a relationship,
we know that it's like a constant battle to appreciate the other person, right?
It's a constant battle to make sure we're not taking them for granted.
Or maybe you're a kid, live at home with your parents.
And, you know, it's so easy just to feel like,
well, yeah, my parents take care of the cooking and the cleaning.
And yeah, that's just what they do, right?
This is just how it is, you know?
and to not appreciate how hard they work.
What about here at church?
I think there's a lot of people who work really hard here at church
that we might not see, that I might not see, right?
But there's a lot of people doing a lot of stuff to make all this happen.
Our leaders, our pastors, people who serve, ministry teams, right?
How easy is it to just kind of come and feel like, yeah, it just happens.
This just happens, and I just show up, and it's great.
So we might not be idle in the sense of, like, not working,
but are there ways that we could better recognize or support
or appreciate the people who are working hard for us?
You know, one thing that we could do is just ask.
We could ask our partners.
We could ask our leaders, our mentors here at church.
we could ask our parents, hey, do you ever feel taken for granted? Do you ever feel burnt out?
Because I want to appreciate you. I want to love you better, you know? And if there's anything I can
do to lighten that load, let me know. One thing we could do is just ask. A second thing I want us to
see here and reflect on is just kind of as an aside, but, you know, Paul uses some strong and
spiritual language to talk about something that's pretty mundane. Nine to five job. He says,
we command and encourage you in the Lord Jesus Christ to work your boring job. And the people
that don't, Paul says, you're not following the tradition that we set before you. And I think this
says something about our jobs, right? There's something about working a normal job, making a
living, supporting our families, maybe having a little bit extra, hopefully, to share with someone
in need. That's part of our mission. That's part of our calling. It's part of what love one another
means in the church. So do we see that? Do we see our boring work as somehow contributing to
our mission here in the church? So we talked about the idol people. Let's flip it around. Let's talk
about the other people in the church. So imagine, right, these other people who are not idle. They're
working hard. They're giving to the needy. But now they're seeing some other people over here that
are just sitting around. They're idle. They're taking the generosity for granted. How would
they have felt? How would these other people have felt? When I was an undergrad, I did a couple
internships in Austin, Texas. And, you know, I signed up for a gym membership there. And one day
after work, on my way to the gym, I was walking and someone came up to me and asked me for money.
And I decided to stop and give them something. I pulled out my wallet. I didn't have that much
cash, but I, you know, I was like, okay, here's what I have. You know, it was a few dollars.
and I walked away.
As I was walking away, I heard them say behind me,
not, oh, thanks, or God bless.
I heard them say behind me, that's it?
That's it?
And in my head, I was walking and I was like, whoa.
Because stuff was happening in my head.
I got really angry.
And I was surprised by how strong I felt about it
and how long I thought about it afterwards, right?
Because I didn't have to give you anything.
I didn't have to stop, right?
Probably a lot of people,
that's a lot of people for money.
A lot of them probably don't stop.
I didn't have to give you anything
and I gave you what I had in my wallet.
And this is the response that I get.
I had a lot to reflect on, right?
I think God used that to bring up
a lot of stuff in my heart.
I had to confess.
I had to talk to God.
but I share this experience because I think this kind of experience
has the potential to make us close up our hearts, right?
To say, all right, I'm not going to do that anymore
because if this is what happens when I try and do something good,
I mean, I'm just not going to do that anymore.
I'm just not.
And if this happens between people in the church,
That can cause a lot of damage, right?
A lot of damage.
So how would these other church members have felt?
Well, they're faithfully giving, again, to meet other people's needs.
They're seeing people take advantage of it.
That would have been so discouraging, right?
So emotionally draining.
I thought we were all in this together.
I thought we're doing something here, right?
We're a family.
We're brothers and sisters in God's family.
but now I realize that these people, they don't seem to value this community and these relationships
as much as I do. And there's a risk of saying, okay, yeah, if this is what happens when I
try and do something good, it's not worth it. I'm not doing it anymore. This really threatens
the relationships in the church, and it really threatens the mission of the church.
and I think this is why Paul gives the strong commands that he does right he does this because
he wants to protect the church's relationships and mission so as we look into the last part of
our passage we'll see Paul give these commands and I think he's trying to protect the church's
relationship and mission let's read the last part of our passage as for you brothers and sisters
do not grow weary in doing good.
If anyone does not obey what we say in this letter,
take note of that person,
have nothing to do with him,
that he may be ashamed.
Do not regard him as an enemy,
but warn him as a brother.
Now may the Lord of peace himself
give you peace at all times in every way.
The Lord be with you all.
I, Paul, write this greeting with my own hand.
This is the sign of genuineness
in every letter of mine.
It's the way that I write.
the grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you all. I really love how in verse 13, I think Paul
understands what the rest of the church is going through, right? He says, don't grow weary of doing
good. The rest of the church is feeling like, dude, I'm making a genuine effort here, and it's just
being wasted. It's just being wasted. And Paul says, yeah, listen, I understand how you feel,
and listen, we're going to make some necessary changes. We're going to have to do some discipline
here, but I don't want you to give up on loving each other. I don't want you to give up on the
calling of the church, of the mission of the church, of loving each other and taking care
of those who are really in need. Because remember, there are people really in need among you, and you
need to love those people. And remember Jesus, right? Jesus knew he would be rejected, right? He knew he
would come and try and love people, but he would be rejected, and Jesus probably felt at times
that he was wasting his time, right? And on top of that, I think Jesus knows us. He knows us as his
followers, we take him for granted, right? We take Jesus' love and grace for granted sometimes,
and he still loves us. So don't give up. Don't grow weary of doing good, right? Church, don't
give up. So again, when Paul says, if you don't work, you don't eat, right? When he says that,
it's not about, okay, if someone's in a bad situation, they don't have enough to eat,
it's their own fault, right? It's not about that. It's not about, if you're not contributing enough,
if you don't provide enough shareholder value to the church, you're out. It's not about that.
Because right after Paul says, if you don't work, you don't eat, he says this. He says,
don't grow weary of doing good. Keep doing good. Keep being generous. Keep being sacrificial.
So Paul's purpose for the church is to keep doing those things, but to be wise and sustainable
in doing good so that they can keep loving and keep caring and giving to serve others and not
grow tired. By the way, as an aside, this is the same heart behind passages like 1 Timothy 5
where it says, Paul says, let the church not be burdened so that it can assist those who are
really widows, the people who really have no one to take care of them, right? Let the church not be
burdened so that it can continue to love, continue to care for those in need. So what about us? Are
we growing weary of doing good? Is there an area of our lives where we see ourselves slowly getting
tired? We're getting tired of caring for that person. We're getting tired of praying for that
friend. We're tired of trying to lead others toward Jesus and not seeing any fruit, right? It's a waste
time, I think Paul understands that. And I think Jesus understands that. And I think it's worth
asking, okay, maybe are there some wise practical changes that we might have to make if we're feeling
burnt out like that, right? That's what this passage is about, is making a change. But whatever
change we make, I hope that it won't be a change that reflects a closing of our heart, a stepping
away from the work of love. But I would hope that it's a choice, it's a change that we make so that
we can continue to follow Jesus's example of love and servanthood for the long haul, right, sustainably.
Let's move on to verses 14 and 15. We're going to see Paul give these really, you know, kind of
serious consequences for people who continue to live in idleness. Verse 14, 15 says this,
if anyone does not obey what we say in this letter, take note of that person, have nothing to do with
him, that he may be ashamed. Do not regard him as an enemy, but warn him as a brother. So I want to
talk a little bit about Paul's use of shame here. Paul is explicitly saying, I'm doing this because
I want these people to feel ashamed. In fact, he's already kind of shaming them by calling them out
in this letter. Some of you might know that in the ancient world, not everyone could read, right? So
the way that these letters would be heard is, okay, the whole church gathers together, and one person
will read it out loud. So everyone's listening to it together, and the people who are idle, right,
they were part of the church too, so they were probably there with everyone else. So you can
imagine, you know, let's say, I don't know, Gaius, one of the idle people, right? He's like munching
on some bread listening to this letter and you know paul says grace to you and peace we always
give thanks for you amen amen amen the lord will guard you from the evil one
i really love this guy paul he's such a great writer right paul says i command you to keep
away from those who are idle choosing not to work eating the bread of others and putting a burden
on them. Oh, awkward. Is he talking about me? Paul's using shame here, right? He is calling
these people out publicly. And that might make some of us uncomfortable because, you know, some
of us have experienced how shame really can become like a big stronghold in our life, right,
that we struggle with. And some of us have experienced shame being used, you know, being weaponized or
being used to manipulate. And I get that. I want to recognize that discomfort that some of us might
feel. But I want to share with you something that I read in a book. This book is called
The Other Side of Church. It's written jointly by a psychologist and a theologian. And I found it to
be a little bit provocative, but kind of illuminating. I hope you will as well. Let me
read it for you. It says, brain science tells a more nuanced story than shame equals bat. I can
still remember when Jim, that's the psychologist, first explained the neuroscience of shame. He said
that neuroscience reveals that shame is necessary for character to change. Our brain has dedicated
circuits that control the formation of character. Shame is important for socialization, and without
it, our character will not change. That's kind of surprising, right? When I read this, I was kind
of surprised. It's saying that we as humans don't really change without a little bit of shame.
And don't get me wrong, there is toxic shame. There is a kind of shame that is absolutely toxic. It
should not have any place in our relationships in the church or outside of the church, right? But
it's not always like that. Sometimes shame is just a natural social signal that we've done something
wrong, and that something needs to change. Let me give you an example. Let's say we're hanging out
with friends, we're laughing, right, and having a good time, and let's say I say something insensitive
about someone, and you can see them hearing that, yeah, they're laughing, and then they kind of
suddenly like, oh, your face changes. And if I see that, I feel bad. I get a bad feeling because I
realize it's a signal to me that I went a little bit too far. Okay, I need to change. I need to be
a little bit more careful about how I speak. So that bad feeling of shame is temporary, but it's
a wake-up call that hopefully leads me to a good change that will make our relationship better
in the future. So how can we confront someone or correct someone without it leading to toxic shame?
This is from the book, but it's also kind of common sense, right? So like in general,
if we confront someone and we're just condemning, we're just lashing out, right? That for sure is
going to lead to toxic shame, right? Example, I can't believe you did such a crappy job, man. You
never listen. Translation, you're lazy, you're incompetent, right? You're not like us, right? We
do a good job. I don't know why you can't. You're, you know, you're just bad, and you're not a part
of us. It's pushing people out. It's telling them, okay, there's nothing you can do. I'm attacking
your identity, and I think it's clear why this could lead to, you know, toxic shame that can lead
to long-term hurt and strongholds in our life.
Now, on the other hand,
if we confront someone and we name the failing,
we name what went wrong, we do need to do that,
while at the same time affirming our relationship with them,
you know, this might still cause some shame.
No one likes being confronted, right?
It'll probably feel a little bit bad,
but hopefully this bad feeling leads to good change
and a stronger relationship.
Example, hey, listen, we hold this job really highly.
This is really important to us, and we take it seriously.
So, you know, you're a member of our group, you're a member of our team, we want you as
a member of our team, but listen, we, I hope that you're going to take this a little bit
more seriously as a member of our team.
So we're communicating that something needs to change, but at the same time, we're communicating
we want you to change because you're part of us. We want you as a part of our team, as a part of
our community, and that's why we're telling you this. And I think Paul is using shame in the second
way. He's using it in a way that is trying to invite the idlers back into relationship.
How can we see this? Well, look in verse 6, where he says, okay, keep away from any brother or sister
who is walking in idleness.
They're still brothers and sisters, right?
Same as verse 15.
Don't regard them as enemies,
but warn them as brothers and sisters.
So it's not about revenge.
It's not about lashing out.
It's done in hope, right?
It's hoping that they're gonna see,
hey, guys, what you're doing
is causing a really big problem in our community,
but we want you as part of our community.
So please recognize the problem
and recognize how you can change.
We want you here.
and we can also see this in verse 12, right, Paul says, we command and encourage these people
in the Lord Jesus Christ to work and earn their own living, so he's saying, guys, people who are
idle, remember Jesus, right, remember why you're here, you're part of this community because
you follow Jesus, Jesus came to show us how to have true life, and true life is not about getting
through life as comfortably as possible, right? You guys remember that? You guys remember that
Jesus taught us that true life is about serving others, about being loved by others, right?
So remember why you're here. So again, this is a, it's a tough command, right? It's a tough
command, and there are consequences. But I think Paul's intent is to restore the relationships
and protect the church's mission. A final question I want to ask here as we close. What about grace?
We've talked a lot about working and consequences in this passage.
Where is grace in this passage?
You know, I think this chapter really illustrates that sometimes you have these complicated situations
where it takes wisdom to even know what grace and love look like in this situation.
Right, on the one hand, you have these people, and you don't kick them out just for doing something wrong once, right?
We don't do that, right?
you show grace to them. But on the other hand, you have these people who are in need, right? And the
resources are limited. They need to eat. You got to show grace to them. And on the other other hand,
right, you have these other people who are being burnt out. They're giving, but they're feeling
like, dude, I can't keep doing this. You got to show grace to them. So sometimes love and grace
are complicated because sometimes life is complicated. And I think this passage is an
example of Paul walking with the church to hopefully have wisdom and grace even as they
make some of these hard decisions. But notice that Paul is also always drawing everyone's attention
back to the central mission of the church, right? Remember why we're here. Remember Jesus. So as we
close, some closing reflections for us. Are there ways that we're taking others' hard work for
granted? Are there people in our lives that we want to better appreciate or support? Are we
becoming weary of doing good? Maybe we have to make a change, but what heart are we going to have
as we think about making that change? And maybe some of us are in a complex situation where it
takes wisdom to know what grace and love look like. Sometimes this happens when there's relational
conflict, right? There's multiple parties involved, and you have to consider, okay, how do I stop the
hurt from spreading here, but at the same time, we need to give people second chances, and also we
need to set boundaries here, but we don't want to push people away, right? What does that look like?
I really believe that if you're in this situation, that's an opportunity for us, where we can
really experience what it feels like to be filled with the Spirit of God. Now, it doesn't make the
twice easy. It doesn't make the, you know, dealing with this easy, but I think it's an amazing
feeling to feel like God is with us as we're walking through this hard situation with his
wisdom and love. So pray to be filled by the Spirit. Let's pray as we close. God, sometimes life
is complicated. Sometimes being in the church is complicated. And God, we know that you've called
us all, you're calling us all back to this heart of love, this heart of sacrifice that you showed
for us. But we also know, Lord, that there's wisdom involved in how we live that out in the church.
God, so fill us with the Spirit. Help us to be people who have your wisdom and have your love.
And help us, Lord, as we navigate these situations, Lord, to be people who deal with these things
differently. That we can always make choices, even if we have to do something difficult. That we
always have this heart of wanting to follow in your example more. God, you're our example. Jesus,
what you did is our example, and we want to follow you. So help us to do that and fill us
with your spirit. I pray this in your name. Amen.